International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Lodge 707 Records 1984.0014
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers, Lodge 707 Records
undated, 1952-2002
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0014
18 Linear Feet
Chartered in 1974, representing machinists at United Aircraft's Pratt and Whitney plant in North Haven, Connecticut. Originally organized as the United Automobile Workers Local 1234 in 1952.
History
The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers Lodge 707 was chartered on 11 September 1974. The local represents machinists at United Aircraft's Pratt and Whitney North Haven Plant. The workers, about 1685 men and 615 women, as of 1984, make blades, forms and jet engine parts.
Lodge 707 was originally organized on 10 November 1952 as United Automobile Workers Local 1234. Local 1234 was decertified on 5 May 1972. The machinists then formed the Independent Aircraft Machinists Union, but about 500 workers continued paying UAW dues. Pratt and Whitney recognized only the Independent and not the UAW Local 1234 after decertification.
At the same time, during the late 1960s and early 1970s, there were several machinists, including Ed Joseph, Harry Miller and Pete LaRosa, who were actively working to join the International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers. In addition, other Pratt and Whitney plants were already affiliated with IAMAW.
In 1974, the Independent and UAW formed a "No Raid Agreement", and agreed to go into IAMAW.
On 30 September 2002, Lodge 707 merged with IAMAW Lodge 1746, when the Pratt & Whitney plant in North Haven closed and the workers transferred to the East Hartford plant.
Chronology
1952 November 10 - 1972 May 5 UAW Local 1234
1972 May 5 - 1974 September 11 IAMU ("Independent")
1974 September 11 -2002 September 30 IAMAW Lodge 707
Scope and Content
The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers Lodge 707 records are arranged in twelve series. The overall arrangement is chronological, reflecting the different affiliations and name changes the local has undergone. Access to grievance, arbitration, and compensation files is restricted.
Arrangement
Series I: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Administrative Files (undated, 1952-1972) is arranged in two subseries. Agreements includes contract and contract negotiation materials from 1953 to 1969. Subject Files includes the original 1952 charter for Local 1234, minutes of the Executive Board, incoming and outgoing correspondence, correspondence with Pratt and Whitney, and material concerning the independent union controversy in the late 1960s.
Series II: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Scrapbooks (1960-1966) contains two scrapbooks of newsclippings and photographs documenting the 1960 machinists strike at United Aircraft, and general activities of Lodge 707 and other machinist unions activities.
Series III: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Arbitrations (1954-1971) contains general correspondence and lists concerning arbitrations and individual cases arranged alphabetically by last name. This series also contains two National Labor Relations Board cases. Access to arbitration files is restricted.
Series IV: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Grievance Material (1954-1972) is arranged in three subseries. Grievance Administration includes correspondence, lists and reports. General Grievance includes forms, notes, correspondence, and other material documenting union grievance of a general nature, arranged alphabetically by type of grievance. Grievance 1954-1971 [RESTRICTED] contains grievance forms, notes and correspondence relating to individual grievances. Material is arranged chronologically and then alphabetically by name.
Series V: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Workmen's Compensation Cases (1960-1972) contains correspondence, forms and notes. These cases are arranged alphabetically by name of individual and type of case, or chronologically by year. Access to compensation files is restricted.
Series VI: Job Descriptions (undated, 1965-1978) contains standard forms describing machinist job qualifications and responsibilities at the Pratt and Whitney plant.
Series VII: Independent Aircraft Machinists Union: Administrative Files (1969-1974) includes minutes, correspondence, newsletters and memorabilia. This material is arranged by type.
Series VIII: Independent Aircraft Machinists Union: Grievances (1972-1974) includes grievance forms, correspondence and notes documenting individual grievances. Grievances for 1972-1973 are arranged alphabetically by name. Year and shift organize grievances for 1973-1974. Access to grievance files is restricted.
Series IX: International Association Of Machinists And Aerospace Workers Lodge 707, Administrative Files (>undated, 1972-2002) is arranged in four subseries. Minutes contains minutes of the Executive Board, Membership, and Delegates meetings for 1973-1977. Subject Files (1972-1977) includes contract negotiations, correspondence, membership lists, reports, and financial material arranged alphabetically by subject. General Correspondence (1974-1977) contains incoming and outgoing correspondence arranged chronologically. Employee Service Records (1972-1981) [RESTRICTED], are computer-printed listings of active employees, provided monthly by the company to the union as stipulated by the union contract. They are listed alphabetically by name of employee, by clock number, or by department number. The records provide important data on the production workforce, including race, sex, employment and promotion dates, pay grades, etc. The more recent years also note union membership. Archives Staff took a one month (December) sample per year. This subseries is arranged chonologically.
Series X: International Association Of Machinists And Aerospace Workers Lodge 707: Grievance Material (1974-1978) [RESTRICTED] includes individual merit grievances, forms, correspondence, and notes arranged alphabetically by name. Access to grievance files is restricted.
Series XI: Printed Material (undated, 1960-1983) includes publications of the AFL-CIO, IAMAW, Occupational Safety and Health Administration, local newsletters, and union songs. Material is arranged alphabetically by creating body.
Series XII: 2002 additions to collection (1993-2002) Includes framed charters and supplements, the April 2001 report "Grow Good Jobs in Connecticut", and extensive U.S. Court of Appeals rulings and other documents relating to the 2000 efforts by the IAMAW to prevent United Technologies Pratt & Whitney from breaking a collective bargaining agreement.
Custodial History
The United Auto Workers Local 1234 and Independent Aircraft Machinists Union records were transferred to IAMAW Local 707 in 1974. When the local was chartered, these records became working "historical files" of Local 707.
Acquisition Information
The International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers Lodge 707 records were deposited in the Connecticut Labor Archives on February 13, 1984, by Gary Nielsen, President of the Local. An addition to the collection was made in September 2002. The deposit was changed to a donation in February 2003 with the execution of a Deed of Gift between Local 707 and Archvies & Special Collections.
Access
The collection is open and available for research with the exception of grievance, arbitration and compensation files.
Notebooks; Correspondence; Grievance procedures; Connecticut (state); Machinists; New Haven (inhabited place); Collective labor agreements; Labor; Workers' compensation; Independent unions; Aerospace industries; Administrative records; Employees; Publications (documents); Labor unions; Aircraft industry; Actions and defenses; Aircraft industry workers; Financial Records; Fliers (printed matter); United Technologies Corporation; United Aircraft Corporation; United Aircraft Corporation. Pratt & Whitney Aircraft Division
- Series I: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Administrative Files, undated, 1952-1972
  - Agreements
    - 1953 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - 1954 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - 1955 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - 1958 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Contract Negotiations, 1962 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
    - Contract Negotiations, 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - 1966 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Contract Negotiations, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 8-9)
  - Subject Files
    - Charter, 1952 November 10 (Box OS:, Folder 10)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - Ames vs. United Aircraft: Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Atlas vs. United Aircraft: Correspondence, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Attorney correspondence: Baker and Diamond, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Attorney correspondence: Rubenstein, Droisen and Rubenstein, 1960, 1962 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - COMP Master lists, undated (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1970-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - Discrimination allocations at Pratt and Whitney, 1971-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - D O's, 1968-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - Dues and assessment materials, 1968-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - Error cause identification, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Evitts, George: election and presidency, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
    - Grievance procedure manual, undated (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Honorary members, IAMU, 1972 May 5 (Box 22)
    - IAMAW proposals to United Aircraft, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - IAMAW—UAW collective bargaining program, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
    - Independent union controversy: expulsion of members from local 1234, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
    - Independent union controversy: letters and forms, 1969-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 29-30)
    - Insurance: correspondence, 1967-1968 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
    - Insurance and population, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
    - Jet News, 1969-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
    - La Rose, Michael: correspondence, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
    - Members, list of, 1972 June (Box OS)
    - Newsclippings, 1966-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
    - Population of Plant, 1968-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 36-37)
    - Pratt and Whitney: excusal letters, 1968-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 38-40)
    - Pratt and Whitney: general correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
    - Roll of Local 1234 UAW-CIO members, 1953 September (Box OS)
    - Rocker, Gerry, International Rep.: correspondence, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 42)
    - Schiller, Leonard, International Rep.: correspondence, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 43)
    - Scoville Manufacturing Company and Local 1604, 1959, 1965, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
    - Sikorsky Teamsters Local 1150 and United Aircraft: agreement, 1972 February (Box 1:, Folder 45)
    - Skilled Trades Council, 1968-1969 (Box 1:, Folder 46)
    - Skilled Trades work records, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 47)
    - Stewards: appointments, 1968-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 48-49)
    - Stewards: resignations, 1960, 1968-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 50-52)
    - Steward training, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 53)
    - Transfers, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 54)
    - United Aircraft: brochures, 1965, 1968, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 55)
    - United Auto Workers dues programs, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 56)
    - United Auto Workers: International correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 57)
    - Unsanitary bathroom conditions at the plant, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 58)
    - Veterans, 1967-1968 (Box 1:, Folder 59)
    - Veterans vacation pay, 1967 (Box 1:, Folder 60)
    - Working conditions improvement petitions, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 61)
    - Memorabilia, undated (Box 1:, Folder 62)
- Series II: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Scrapbooks, 1960-1966
  - Newsclippings, 1960-1962 (Box 2:, Folder 63)
  - Newsclippings and photographs, 1960-1966 (Box 2:, Folder 64-72)
- Series III: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Arbitrations, 1954-1971
- Series IV: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Grievance Material, 1954-1972
- Series V: United Auto Workers Local 1234: Workmen's Compensation Cases, 1960-1972
- Series VI: Job Descriptions, undated, 1965-1978
  - Job code book, undated (Box 12:, Folder 714)
  - Descriptions, 1965-1978 (Box 12:, Folder 715-731)
  - Descriptions, 1965-1978 (Box 13:, Folder 732-748)
- Series VII: Independent Aircraft Machinists Union: Administrative Files, undated, 1969-1974
  - Correspondence, undated, 1974 (Box 14:, Folder 749)
  - Independent union controversy: letters and leaflets, 1969 (Box 14:, Folder 750)
  - Minutes, 1972-1974 (Box 14:, Folder 751)
  - New Union News, 1971 November - 1972 October (Box 14:, Folder 752)
  - Memorabilia, undated (Box 14:, Folder 753)
- Series VIII: Independent Aircraft Machinists Union: Grievances, 1972-1974
- Series IX: International Association Of Machinists And Aerospace Workers Lodge 707: Administrative Files, undated, 1972-2002
  - Minutes
    - Executive Board and Membership meetings, undated, 1973-1977 (Box 17:, Folder 778-783)
  - Subject Files
    - Charter, 1974 (Box 22)
    - Supplement to Charter, undated
    - Contract negotiations, 1974 (Box 17:, Folder 784)
      - District 91
        - Business Representative weekly reports, 1975 (Box 17:, Folder 785)
        - Correspondence, 1974-1977 (Box 17:, Folder 786)
        - Election rules, undated (Box 17:, Folder 787)
        - Executive Board Delegates meeting, 1975-1976 (Box 17:, Folder 788-789)
    - Editor's seminar notes, undated (Box 17:, Folder 790)
    - Education: labor schools, 1976-1977 (Box 17:, Folder 7917)
    - Escapees: letters of resignation from 707, 1975 (Box 17:, Folder 792)
    - Excusal letters, 1974-1976 (Box 17:, Folder 793)
    - Financial reports, 1974-1977 (Box 17:, Folder 794)
    - Greater New Haven Central Labor Council Delegates meetings, 1975-1977 (Box 17:, Folder 795)
    - Insurance settlements: attorney's correspondence, 1975-1977 (Box 17:, Folder 796)
    - Investigation of a Possible Brain Cancer Cluster at Pratt & Whitney by the CT Department of Public Health (mounted board), 2002 (Box OS)
    - Membership lists, 1974-1977 (Box 17:, Folder 797)
    - Notices, 1975-1976 (Box 17:, Folder 798)
    - O.S.H.A., 1976 (Box 17:, Folder 799)
    - O.S.H.A.: Testimony of W. Winpisinger RE: noise pollution, 1975 July 7 (Box 17:, Folder 800)
    - Pratt and Whitney: citations for alleged safety and health violations, 1975 (Box 17:, Folder 801)
    - Property, 1976 (Box 17:, Folder 802)
    - Resignations, 1975-1977 (Box 17:, Folder 803)
    - Safety and Health Committee: correspondence and reports, 1972 (Box 17:, Folder 804)
    - Shop stewards election, 1975 (Box 17:, Folder 805)
    - "Union Stewards" roster, undated (Box 17:, Folder 806)
  - General Correspondence
    - undated, 1974-1977 (Box 17:, Folder 807-813)
- Series X: International Association Of Machinists And Aerospace Workers Lodge 707: Grievance Material, undated, 1974-1978
- Series XI: Printed Material, undated, 1960-1983
  - AFL-CIO: general, ca. 1960s-1970s (Box 20:, Folder 997)
  - Connecticut State Council of Machinists, AFL-CIO: "June News", 1975 (Box 20:, Folder 998)
  - Greater New Haven Central Labor Council: Occupational Safety and Health Conference, 1972 February 26 (Box 20:, Folder 999)
  - "Health Center News", 1968 (Box 20:, Folder 1000)
  - Industry safety and health publications, 1967, 1971-1972 (Box 20:, Folder 1001)
    - International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers
      - Aerospace conference, 1974 May 17 (Box 20:, Folder 1002)
      - "Aerospace Update", 1978 (Box 20:, Folder 1003)
      - Art and Feature Service for local newsletters, undated (Box 20:, Folder 1004)
      - "Diesel Line", 1976 (Box 20:, Folder 1005)
      - Flyers, 1971, 1973-1977, 1983 (Box 20:, Folder 1006-1012)
      - General publications, ca. 1970s (Box 20:, Folder 1013)
      - "Keeping in Touch", 1976 (Box 20:, Folder 1014)
      - "Safety-Gram", 1974-1975 (Box 20:, Folder 1015)
      - "Shop Talk", 1976-1977 (Box 20:, Folder 1016-1017)
      - "Tune-up", 1976 (Box 20:, Folder 1018)
  - "Joint Study for the Analysis of the Bridgeport Regional Economy in the Event of a Reduction of Defense Allocations", 1968 November 1 (Box 20:, Folder 1019)
  - Local Newsletter samples, 1974 (Box 20:, Folder 1020)
  - "The Machinist", 1972, 1976 (Box 20:, Folder 1021)
  - National Safety Council: Publications, 1967, 1972 (Box 20:, Folder 1022)
  - "New Unity", 1977, 1981 (Box 20:, Folder 1023)
  - Newsclippings: national labor issues, 1968 (Box 20:, Folder 1024)
    - Occupational Safety and Health Administration
      - Federal Register, 1972 (Box 20:, Folder 1025)
      - General Publications, 1971-1974 (Box 20:, Folder 1026-1027)
      - Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 20:, Folder 1028)
      - Safety and Health Standards Digest, 1975 (Box 20:, Folder 1029)
  - Pratt and Whitney Aircraft "Power Plant", 1966, 1968, 1972 (Box 20:, Folder 1030)
  - "Railway Clerk", 1973 April (Box 20:, Folder 1031)
  - "The 707 Counselor", 1976 (Box 20:, Folder 1032)
  - "The 707 Gap", 1976 (Box 20:, Folder 1033)
  - "Survival Kit", 1973 (Box 20:, Folder 1034)
  - Union songs and scoresheets, undated (Box 20:, Folder 1035)
  - United Auto Workers 13th Aerospace Conference, 1968 February 27 - 28 (Box 20:, Folder 1036)
  - United Auto Workers 14th Aerospace Conference, 1971 March 18 - 19 (Box 20:, Folder 1037)
  - US Department of Health, Education and Welfare, Public Health Service: Pamphlets, 1971-1974 (Box 20:, Folder 1038)
  - United Way" "Community Services Bulletin", undated, 1976 (Box 20:, Folder 1039)
  - University of Connecticut, Labor Center: program material, undated, 1965, 1969 (Box 20:, Folder 1040)
- Series XII: 2002 additions, 1993-2002
  - Grievance, between Pratt & Whitney Aircraft Division and Lodge 707 concerning a violation of the collective bargaining agreement, specifically, that of assigning workers of one occupational group to perform tasks within the scope of another occupational group, 1993 (Box 221:, Folder 10421)
  - Documents from the U.S. Court of Appeals and correspondence concerning the action of Lodge 707, under the aegis of Aeronautical Industrial District Lodge no. 91, to prevent United Technologies Pratt & Whitney from violating the collective bargaining agreement by cutting the workforce at the P&W and other UTC divisions. (Case No. 3:99CT01827), 2000 (Box 21:, Folder 1042-1045)
  - "Social Cost Analysis of the Impact of Closing of UTC's Aircraft Engine and Parts Plants in Connecticut," by Ken Blum, Center for Labor & Community Research, Chicago, IL, 2002 (Box 21:, Folder 1046)
  - "Grow Good Jobs in Connecticut, High Tech Manufacturing at the Crossroads." Report written by Robert Forrant and Jennifer Zelnick of the University of Massachusetts Lowell, Department of Regional Economic and Social Development. Executive Summary and Report, 2002 (Box 21:, Folder 1047)